I've done it before where I only pushed it once and I thought it was recording and I did a five-hour interview.
And none of it was recording.
None of it was recording.
Oh, geez.
Yeah.
Yes.
So today is May 8th, 2026.
My name is Caitlin Sheets and I am here with Dr. G. Cliff Lamb.
We're conducting this interview in the AgLife Science Building on the campus of Texas A&M University in College Station, Texas.
The interview is part of the Coral History Project documenting the experiences of Aggies.
Yes.
sure yeah so yeah thanks a lot for taking the time um to chat so i have a very unique background i actually grew up in zimbabwe africa so south central africa on a beef cattle dairy corn and tobacco operation and so throughout my whole career i was very interested in agriculture i knew at a very young age i was going to come to the u.s and study
And so in the late 80s, I came and I studied at Middle Tennessee State University, got my bachelor's degree, and then went to Kansas State and got my master's and PhD.
I've always been highly passionate in reproductive biology.
and using reproduction to increase efficiency of livestock operations so so that's uh that was my uh formal education and then from there i had full intentions to go back to africa at that point that was always my goal and in the late 1990s early 2000s
there was a big push by the government of Zimbabwe to nationalize all of the farms and ranches, or most of them.
So basically, the operation I grew up on and many of the operations
those operations were nationalized.
And so there was not a real large incentive for me to return to Africa because we didn't really have anything that we could sort of take over and operate.
And so I took a position at the University of Minnesota as a faculty member.
I spent 10 years as a faculty member at the University of Minnesota and loved it.
Really enjoyed being there.
Following that, I was asked to essentially do some work as an administrator and a faculty member at the University of Florida.
And I was there for about 10 years.
And then about, I'm in my 10th year now at Texas A&M.
And, you know, I came here as the department head in March of 2017 as department head of animal science.
I spent five years as department head of animal science and also interim department head for ecology and conservation biology, another department on campus.
At that time, that department was restructured with wildlife and fisheries.
into two separate departments and i served as the interim department head for rangeland wildlife and fisheries management at the same time as being department head of animal science yeah it sure is and uh but it but a great experience and then uh in december of 2021 the chancellor of the texas amy university system had called me and asked me if i would
be interested in being the director of AgriLife Research.
And so I saw a lot of opportunity, a lot of opportunity to grow our agency and took that position.
And I've been in this role since January of 2022.
Fabulous.
Many roles and much experience.
For someone who is ignorant, going back a little bit on what you're talking about, what does it mean when
they took the farms, the ranches, and made it state?
Yeah, so they nationalized about 6,000 farms and ranches.
In other words, the government took them away from the landowners.
Most people whose farms were taken, they had about 90 days to leave the land.
And then they basically...
redistributed the land to other people either people from the city or government officials received land yeah hugely disruptive and really what it did Zimbabwe for people who don't know was had the reputation the name of being the breadbasket of Africa
So we were producing enough food to feed the whole country, and we exported a ton of food to neighboring countries.
And within three years, we were producing less than 20% of the food that we were producing three years before as a result of the nationalization.
And Zimbabwe's economy at the time was largely driven on agriculture.
and the economy imploded to the point that inflation was so bad that it was over 175 percent a day inflation was um it was it was a real disaster so basically the the country went bankrupt yeah yeah so thank you for the history yeah that is out yeah out to the people who yeah absolutely yeah um
Sorry, just digesting.
Yeah.
So you said you were always interested in cattle and reproductive aspect of it.
What kind of drew you to that?
So growing up on a fairly large ranch and farm, we farmed and ranched.
And so we had dairy cattle and we had beef cattle.
And from a very young age, I'm not sure what it was that drew me to specifically reproduction in cattle.
I was highly passionate about
about livestock, I mean, from a very, very young age, as early as I can remember.
I just loved working on the farm.
But we had a neighbor that was one of the only people in the country who did
embryo transfer.
And embryo transfer is basically taking embryos from genetically superior animals and causing that cow to produce more than she normally does and then taking those embryos and transferring them to surrogates or recipients that are not as genetically good but they give birth to a genetically superior animal.
and so I used to just I loved I mean when he was doing it on our farm it just sort of captured my attention and when I was in elementary school in fact nobody in my family can remember me ever not talking about specializing in reproduction right I was that that's what I my whole life that's what I was just passionate about and so throughout high school I
I learned to artificially inseminate cows at a very young age.
I was in high school, very early in high school, and very fortunate to have had the opportunity then to specialize in that through my career as a researcher.
That's absolutely fascinating.
It's not just that you're interested in cattle, but it's a very specific part of the cattle, too.
Wow.
What drew you to specifically the academic and research side of things rather than the industry side of things?
really good question um to be perfectly honest my goal after i got a phd was to return and use the skills that i'd developed in growing agriculture back in zimbabwe and and that was to not only improve production efficiency of cattle operations beef cattle or dairy operations but i also had a passion in wildlife and so
potentially utilizing the skills that I'd learned to then do some conservation work.
So preserving genetics of endangered species and things like that.
When I got word that I was not going to be able to go back and do anything on the farm or ranch, I sort of had a choice to either go into the U.S. industry on the commercial side, working with either a pharmaceutical company or a nutrition company or working in the industry somewhere or starting my own company,
or to go into research.
And while I was working on my PhD, I became really intrigued.
It was a very interesting time of year for where I had an interest.
And we were at that time developing a system to inseminate cows where we did not have to know when they were in heat.
So we call it fixed-timed artificial insemination.
So you take a group of cows, and typically you would have to make sure that the cow was receptive to become pregnant, right?
She would be in heat.
Right.
And so if you had, say, 100 cows, if you wanted to get them all pregnant, you go out there and watch them and see when they come in heat, then you artificially inseminate them.
We were in the process at that time of developing a system where you could inseminate them all at the same time on the same day, and it just makes things more efficient for a producer.
So we'd started working on that while I was in my PhD, and I thought, you know, this is an opportunity to have a significant global impact in production systems for beef cattle where you can use reproduction to improve production efficiency of cattle operations.
Yeah.
And so the first 10 years of my research career, that really was my primary focus, is refining that system, working on products that were not approved in this country at the time, working to get them approved so that cattle producers had access to those products, and then being able to refine it.
excuse me refine it in such a way that it was efficient for cattle producers to to use and you know you go through this process when you're working on your masters and phd that when you first start your masters you really don't understand what research is
to when I finished my PhD, you know, I was really intrigued by the scientific method, the process, okay, and understanding all of the things that have been done and then coming up with ideas to make a difference in the future.
And so by the time I finished my PhD, I could see myself in a role.
Yeah, exactly.
Is that system still in use today?
Absolutely.
So I'll give you some examples.
You know, when we started, so between 1997 and 2003 is sort of when we really developed and refined these systems.
More than half of the cows that are artificially inseminated in the U.S. today use the system we developed in 2003.
And so that is happening today.
And we also, in 2002, we started what's called the Beef Reproduction Task Force.
And so it was scientists who work in the space around the country.
A few of us got together to start the task force.
And we came up with a set of recommendations for beef producers to use on what systems to use to get their cows pregnant to artificial insemination.
about half of the protocols that are on that sheet were ones that we played, we developed or played a major role in developing.
And so in the U.S., very, very fortunate that about 65 to 70 percent of all the heifers that are inseminated right now use a protocol that we had a hand in developing in some way.
And then more than 50 percent of the cows
That's so impressive.
Yeah.
But globally, I think that's even, is where we might have even had a greater role.
And so you take a look, and 2002, 2003 was the first time I visited Brazil.
And Brazil obviously is the next largest beef producer in the world behind the US.
And we started talking about using these systems to get cows pregnant in Brazil.
At the time, less than a million cows in Brazil were artificially inseminated through fixed-timed artificial insemination.
Today, about 18 million.
every year are inseminated using a a system or a variation of a system we developed in the late 90s and early 2000s so yeah so huge impact there in australia about 75 percent of beef cattle producers that are inseminated use the system we developed
a global kind of impact.
That is so impressive.
What are some things that you've, new things added to it that you've seen in the years?
Yeah, so like I said, in those first 10 years, sort of 97 to 2007, we spent a lot of time refining these systems.
And I've continued to work in that space to even refine things a little bit further.
But we've had the advent of the development of new technologies that then we incorporate into those types of systems.
I'll give you one example.
And very close to us here in Navasota is sexing technologies.
It's a company that has a technology that can sex semen.
And so you can inseminate a cow and the cow will give birth to over 90% accuracy that cow will give birth to a calf that is of a desired sex.
So we took the systems we developed and developed fixed-timed AI systems where you could use sex semen because most of the systems we developed were with conventional semen, and those two products are very different in the way that they're utilized.
Okay.
possible yeah it is it's a it is yes yeah exactly and then obviously i have big interests in um in other reproductive technologies and so i've done a lot of work in in vitro fertilization
a little bit in cloning and it's an area that excites me right now and i have graduate students and postdoc students right now that are working on we call it precision genetics so it's using crispr cas9 which is a gene editing technology
to try and create animals that are more productive.
I mean, we have calves on the ground right now that have been edited for the slick gene.
And so just to explain how that works is that
The slick gene is basically, it's a prolactin receptor.
Prolactin is used for milk, is used for milk, right?
It's a hormone that stimulates milk production.
But at the same time, it's also tied to animals that have about 10% of the hair of the normal kind.
And so we've edited those animals
to have the slick genes so they have 10% of the hair of their full siblings.
So full sibling, two brothers or two sisters can be standing side by side, and the one that's been edited for the slick gene has only 10% of the hair of the other one.
And why is that important?
Well, it's important because in Texas, it's really hot.
And so if they have less hair, they don't spend as much energy trying to cool down during the warm times of the year.
And so when we take the temperature of these animals during the heat of the day, those animals that have this slick gene have a body temperature that's about a degree to a degree and a half less
in the middle of the day than those that have full hair that are full siblings so for warm climates you can ultimately breed these animals and they are more productive they survive better they get they're not as sick there's just a lot of these traits that will help them be more productive and so
How creative.
My first thoughts when I think of science, reproduction, I don't think creative, but that is so creative.
That's right.
Yeah, it is.
And so that's a simple gene to edit.
And obviously that's where we are right now.
You can do an edit to make animals not have horns.
And so...
the reason that you would do that right now in the old days cows needed horns to fight off predators we really don't have to worry about that now but so what so what a lot of people do is they actually have to dehorn the animals manually which becomes it's just not a nice procedure right but if we breed them to not have horns then you don't even have to do that right
Yeah.
But my ultimate goal is to try and create edits that are multifaceted edits that sort of focuses on more than one gene and focus really on the disease side of things.
and the reason for that is that i i want cattle to i want to be able to breed animals that are resistant to certain diseases or ailments that you don't have to treat so you think of what happens then
They're more productive because they don't get sick.
Fewer of them die, fewer of them get sick and so on.
But in addition to that is we have a significant reduction in the use of antibiotics.
And, you know, there's a lot of discussion about antibiotic resistance, right?
And so how do we limit the use of antibiotics in animal agriculture?
And this is one way that I see as a potential solution.
That's so smart.
As you said, two solutions, or two problems, one solution.
One solution, yeah, exactly.
Is there any things that you can share that your protégés are working on?
Yeah, I mean, so right now we have graduate students that are working in anywhere from the really applied side of things.
And when I say applied, it's things that are immediately applicable to a producer, right?
So our results might have application to them this year or next year, right?
And then we have some very fundamental things that results might only help us in 10 or 15 years from now.
So I'll give you an example of something that we're working on in the short term, and that is utilizing different products
to to give to cows around the start of the breeding season so we're not even worrying about whether they're artificially inseminated because still there are so many cows out that you can't handle very easily but if you could just have them once what can you do to treat them that they become pregnant sooner in the breeding season
And they give birth to their calves sooner in the calving season.
And those calves end up becoming a lot more productive than if they don't become pregnant sooner in the breeding season.
So we're working on a couple of projects in that space.
Then sort of in the intermediate space, we have a graduate student right now working on utilizing, doing in vitro fertilization.
And we're using seminal plasma.
So when a bull ejaculates semen, right, there's a lot of, not just the sperm, but there's a lot of fluids around the sperm that has a lot of components.
Well, we have data from multiple bulls that are very high fertility, and we have bulls that are low fertility, right?
And we have all of this data.
And so what we've done is we're collecting seminal plasma from the two groups and then going to see if we can fertilize embryos and understand what it is about the seminal plasma in those two groups that causes differences in fertility.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, it does, absolutely.
And then, obviously, the thing that I talked about is on the gene editing front.
And, yeah, there are several things that we're working on on the gene editing front.
That's very exciting.
A layperson's question.
Yes.
So the insemination, when you inseminate all of them at once instead of having to wait,
Does that create a situation where all of them are pregnant, thus give birth at the same time too?
That's a great question.
Yeah.
So gestation of a cow is about 280 to 285 days.
So about 10 days longer than a human.
And so, yes, they're all pregnant, let's say, on the same day.
And when they go to calve, they're usually spread out at the max about three weeks.
So not unlike humans, right?
Some humans give birth 10 days early and some humans give birth 10 days late.
And so that would be very similar in cattle.
when we do mass inseminate you get somewhere around 50 to 60 percent of them pregnant so not all of them will get pregnant you know and cattle are highly fertile because they've been selected for being fertile because if they don't produce a calf they consume resources so they're so they're eliminated right
So that percentage is very high, 50 to 60 percent for a single offspring bearing species, like a cow that generally only gives birth to one.
They usually only give birth to one animal at a time.
So litters are very different, right?
You can get a pig pregnant almost any time you inseminate her.
You've just got to hope you get more piglets than one or two, right?
But cows only give birth to one.
In comparison, and I give this, I tell people this all the time, so 50% to 60% of those cows get pregnant, but humans are about half that.
Fertility, humans are the least fertile species that give birth to one animal.
Really?
Yes.
Because we don't select humans for fertility.
And, you know, even in the wild, there's selection for fertility, right?
Right.
But humans, we try to figure out ways that every woman who wants to get pregnant, we try and get them pregnant in some way, right?
And so we're a very infertile species.
That really puts it in perspective, too.
And they think whatever, they think everything that they don't give birth all at the same time, because that would be a disaster.
It would, yes.
But it is a lot of people don't realize that
that only about one in three times that they ovulate, and obviously through fertilization and things like that, only about one in three survive in humans.
i did not know that either yeah few people know that yes because a lot of humans don't know that they're pregnant or there's a fertilized egg and the egg dies before they menstruate the next time but yeah it's yeah so yeah
Thank you for going into the little nitty gritties of that.
So when you were in Florida before Texas A&M, how did the opportunity arrive to you for this original position here?
At Texas A&M, yeah.
You know, it's a good question.
I'll go back to when I did two sort of things here.
When I was trying to decide where to go to university when I was growing up in Africa, I was very familiar with Texas A&M and Colorado State.
Those are two universities that I was aware of.
that really did a good job in the reproduction space in the world at the time.
And so I actually applied to those two universities to come to study at that time and ended up going to Middle Tennessee State for a very different reason.
So that was my first sort of thought of Texas A&M.
I had no intention of being a university administrator.
Never thought about it.
It was never really something that I was trying to do.
However, when I was at the University of Florida, I was an administrator with a faculty position, and there were several universities that were asking if I'd be interested in being a department ed.
I had thought that if I was ever going to do that, the place that I would go and do it was at my alma mater, which was Kansas State, and was considering that because I knew the department head was retiring.
At that time, I did get a call from Texas A&M that said, why don't you come and take a look?
I considered it.
I came and took a look.
And I thought that there's probably no university that has the resources
and the desire to be the best right and so after speaking with my wife and my family i said you know i'd be crazy not to take the opportunity because because i think i could make i mean give it the reputation of being the as being the best in the world so that's what that's how i came to the decision
It's so funny to me how things from our past pop up again like that.
You replied to it and it's here again.
Exactly.
Fate.
Yeah, absolutely it was fate.
That's right.
So that decision, was that decision made when they brought you out and you sold the facilities and everything like that too?
Sure.
Yeah, so I think I took four trips out here during the process of when they interviewed me by phone to when I finally took the position.
You know, we had kids that were in high school.
I had to make sure that they were comfortable moving here at the time.
And then at the same time, I wanted to learn more about what are some of the things that seem to be, should I say, slowing them down or not giving them the opportunity to
be recognized outside of Texas as one of the better animal science departments in the country or the world.
And, you know, most of that stuff was probably just decisions that I thought I could make.
And, yeah, and we did.
Fantastic.
Yeah.
So when you arrived here, what were your first impressions of the department as well as just the broader Agile culture?
What am I trying to say?
The College of Agriculture.
Yes.
So the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences is the college in which the Department of Animal Science sits.
And so it's one of 15 departments.
The things that I, so first arriving here, the things that I thought were things that they could improve on, right, is fantastic culture, right?
Everybody who graduates from A&M is proud to be from A&M.
And it has this significant impact.
and in their future professions and you know it's a network a lot of people say it's a cult right but it's a very good cult it's a nice cult there are some things that are just very quirky about texas a m that make it unique which which i really enjoy however the one thing that i felt like is that um
that previous decisions in terms of who was hired it tended to be they all tended to have ties to texas a and m and i felt like the way that texas a and m is going to grow especially that department is to consciously find the best person out there and it didn't matter where they're from they could be from some other country
It could be from a different state or different university.
But we needed to broaden the horizon and bring in the best people rather than just saying we have the best people because we taught them here.
Change the way we think about people, change the way that we teach in the classes.
You know, we revamped the...
We revised the curriculum in the department too.
So shortly after I arrived and some of the legwork had already been done before I got here, but we pushed it forward where we wanted more hands-on experiences, things like that, having more labs.
And it's complicated because it's very difficult for a university to have those resources.
But we felt it was going to be important for us to have more hands-on opportunities, ensure we had internship opportunities,
animal experiences.
Actually get out of the classroom.
Yeah, get out the classroom and learn a little bit more beyond the classroom.
Those are all things we implemented.
How is that resolved?
Oh, I think, you know, obviously it was received well because the feedback we got in that process said that that's a big need.
The students like the opportunity.
But what they're really...
took to is some of the new faculty members that we brought in that may not have been Aggies brought a different perspective, right?
And so we changed the perspective, right?
Yeah, exactly.
Do you remember some of those first people that you brought in?
yes i do absolutely and you know it is not not easy for many of them to integrate right but you know they knew that they had my support and i think that that probably helped and and many of those faculty are thriving they're doing extremely well that's fantastic but they're still here yeah that's right that shows that it worked right there yeah because people don't stay in places that they're not happy exactly yeah um
So what were some key questions that you set out to answer throughout your work?
I mean, we've gone over some of them, but even now for questions for the future.
Yeah, so I can share this in a couple of...
So from my research background, some key questions, which we've talked about, is how do you use reproduction to improve production efficiency?
When we hear people talking about sustainability of agricultural systems today, everybody talks about methane and all of these things, right?
And how do you reduce methane in animals?
And there's talks on climate change and the impacts on water and all of those things.
But the number one factor that affects sustainability of livestock operations is getting them pregnant.
And if they're not pregnant, it doesn't matter how much less they consume to produce more or how much less methane or whatever.
they're inefficient, right?
And they're not sustainable.
So using reproduction to increase sustainability of livestock production systems, and we still work on that today.
That's an interesting idea from somebody from the outside that I didn't even think about, that the more efficient the reproduction is, the more sustainable it is.
Absolutely.
The common person doesn't put those two things together often.
Exactly.
Yeah.
You know, and I feel bad that, you know, for some reason, people have taken cows or ruminants.
It's not just cows, but certainly cows are the big thing.
But sheep and goats and said, you know, they're producing greenhouse gases and really it's such a small part of the total greenhouse gas emissions.
that even if we got rid of every cow, we wouldn't change greenhouse gas emissions by more than half a percent, right?
And so if you get rid of every cow, it's not going to change much.
Unfortunately, the general population doesn't understand that because 98% of the population does not work directly in agriculture in this country.
Correct.
And we have a social media.
I mean, everybody makes up their mind on very small snippets of things that they get to believe.
So it's really unfortunate.
There's no context behind it.
Yeah.
That makes sense.
So, you know, questions that I ask now in my role as director of AgriLife Research.
So AgriLife Research is it's a state agency within the Texas A&M University system.
You know, we're on the A&M campus, but we don't just support A&M.
We support all 12 universities and we have locations all over the state.
But yeah, so questions that I really focus on now is how do we continue to figure out ways to produce more food for a growing population of Texas on less and less arable land?
And Texas is particularly different from any other state because 95% of the land in Texas is privately owned.
I do not know that.
Yeah.
So most other states have more public land than Texas does as a percentage.
And we have about 1,500 people moving into Texas every day.
So that's 1,500 extra mouths we have to feed.
The population of Texas is...
over 33 million right now.
And 85% of the population is probably urban, which leaves about 15% more rural and living in more rural regions of the state.
But the problem we have is that we had a lot more arable land previously or land for livestock.
Texas has done very well economically.
People who live in Texas have more resources, so they want a little bit more land.
And so they are now purchasing arable land.
And you see urban regions that were once land that was producing food on, right?
Oh, no.
And so you see all of this segmentation of land going on in Texas that is just gradually eating away at our arable land that we produce the food to feed the population on.
That's concerning.
It is.
And so from my standpoint as director of agri-life research is how do we become even more efficient
on less and less land and to feed a growing population and then the other thing that we have a major problem with is water so you know there's competition now and more and more competition for water for people that is taking it away from
The agricultural use water, right?
And you take a look at what is happening in the Rio Grande Valley, where we've lost an industry like the sugarcane industry is gone because there was not enough water for sugarcane.
Wow.
You go further up the Rio Grande towards West Texas, El Paso, and that region, and a lot of those crops can't be grown.
That used to be grown there.
Vegetables.
It used to be a huge vegetable area.
We can't grow vegetables because the water has become so brackish that they can't put it on the soil, so they can't grow vegetables.
So it's not just cattle?
It's all production, yeah.
And then you go up into the High Plains, so where most of the cattle production is.
So this is where the feedlots are.
Texas is now the third largest dairy state in the country.
And they get their water largely from the Ogallala Aquifer.
And it's not recharging at the rates it should.
So how is that going to impact agriculture 20, 30, 40 years from now?
And so we're trying to find solutions for that.
I have a question, and if you don't want to touch this topic, the first thing that popped in my head when you were talking about limited resources, especially water, is data centers and the conversation around that and water.
Yes.
Is there a meeting or a plan kind of thing?
Yeah, so you may not be aware, but so within AgriLife Research, we have multiple entities that we run.
One entity is called the Texas Water Resource Institute, and it's a statewide effort.
I have a director that reports up to me, and we have these discussions all the time.
So data centers are, you know, there's a lot of discussions about data centers and the use of water.
um and then you have the oil and gas industry that is utilizing a lot of or generating a lot of it's called produced water it's water that is part of the fracking industry right so that's additional water that we are actually getting but it's not very clean you can't drink it right and so
So the discussions we're having right now are can you use some of this water that people can't drink for data centers, for agricultural land, for things like that?
Yeah.
so that you save the potable or the drinking water for the human population.
So that's work that's going on right now.
See, that makes me feel better.
That's something I hope gets put out into the public and they care about that.
Yeah, that's right.
Major concerns, right, with these data centers and storage facilities, right, energy storage facilities.
is water is how they're cooled and how do we utilize water in such a way that it doesn't take away from the current needs.
Can you talk about maybe a project or a finding or something that's
You feel that's a particularly important impact on the production practices here, or at large?
Yeah.
Well, maybe I can touch on one that I think is really important that we're trying to resolve, right?
A lot of people don't realize that Texas has
the largest land ports of entry for agricultural products into the US.
So you can go to Brownwood, Brownsville, sorry, Laredo or El Paso and agricultural products are coming into the US through Mexico.
And then we've got the seaports on the Gulf.
So Corpus Christi, Houston, Galveston.
So you've got all of these agricultural products coming into the US
And at any day, there could be a pathogen, there could be a disease that comes into the U.S. that we don't have a solution for.
And so we spend a lot of time trying to figure out how do we prevent that stuff from being imported.
Because once it gets into Texas, then it can spread through the rest of the U.S.
There's no other state that brings as many and as much agricultural products into the U.S. than we do in Texas.
And so whether it's livestock or crops or vegetables or fruits, whatever it is, there could be a fly on a fruit that comes in.
People don't realize this, but if it gets in and then it spreads, it could destroy some other agricultural industry that we're unaware of.
And so I'll give you some examples.
Right now, you may have heard of the New World Screwworm.
So we're at the forefront of fighting the screwworm.
Our goal is to figure out ways to keep the screwworm from entering the U.S.
Right now, the closest we have a detected screw worm is about 60 miles from the border.
But today that could change, right?
But it's moved all the way from Panama, all the way up to 60 miles from the U.S. border.
So if the screw room gets here and you talked about a production practice, right, it will change the way that livestock and wildlife producers produce their product in South Texas.
It will significantly impact them.
um you know because basically a screw worm is a female only mates once but she'll plant the egg in an open wound of healthy flesh and then that screw basically the lava is just like a screw and it just drills itself into this live flesh
so it's a lot of work and it usually is a wound so it could be where an animal has a bite or there's some infection or some type of laceration or something like that and so on the beef production side when an animal is born where the umbilical cord is
is a perfect place for a screw worm.
Or if you have to dehorn an animal or take the horns off, you create open wounds there.
On the wildlife side, which might be worse than on the livestock side, is when the males are rutting or when they're fighting.
that's the opportunity for them to significantly have screw up.
So it's a it's a huge concern, but it's going to change agricultural production in Texas if it crosses the border.
Yeah.
And when it was here 50, 60, 70 years ago, it did not.
We did not have the wildlife industry we do now.
Most of the landowners in South Texas
were making their money primarily from agriculture, from raising livestock and selling livestock.
it's really difficult just to have a single source of income like livestock.
And so they either have they make money from livestock, wildlife and hunting or oil and gas.
So those three forms in some way, I shouldn't say oil and gas.
It could be renewable energy also.
So wind, solar, things like that.
So there's sort of three forms of income.
If you think that the screwworm gets in here and has an impact on cattle and an impact on wildlife,
Right, that's going to be a significant drain on the landowners in Texas.
That could crash.
Yep.
Absolutely.
Someone from outside of Texas, whenever the screwworm first hit,
Yeah, so and right now as of today, but like I said, I get an update every week As of today, we don't have screw worm in the US.
Okay, and Some some people believe we do but we do not have screw worm in the US Every now and then a human might come back with a screw worm or something
but right now there's no endemic population of screwworms, knock on wood.
The way that it was pushed back in the 1950s, 60s and 70s is the sterile fly technology.
So because a screwworm female only mates once,
we can use irradiation and so we can irradiate lava before they become flies to be sterile okay yeah and so essentially what was done is basically they irradiated these uh these lava they became flies they were not sterile and then those were deployed
where the screw worms were and they deployed enough of them that they over overwhelmed just based on numbers right they overwhelm the population of wild screw worm flies and so it was mostly the sterile males mating
the females and then they basically it wiped them out and pushed them all the way down to Mexico sorry down to Panama through Mexico down to Panama but so there were a lot of these plants so there was a plant in south Texas a plant in Mexico a plant in Nicaragua a plant in Panama that was producing sterile flies every week and that's how they got rid of them
Well, what happened is they stopped, they closed down all of those facilities except for the one in Panama.
And as the screw room was moving north, the Panama facility just couldn't produce enough sterile flies.
That makes sense.
So they're building a new facility in Texas right now to be able to.
Just in case.
Just, yes, to be able to help push those flies back.
Thank you for explaining that to me.
Yeah.
Is there ways your research has changed or evolved over the course of your career as new technologies and new challenges have arrived?
So from my standpoint, I'll talk about it from my research and then as an administrator.
Yeah.
So, yeah, there is no question that my focus has changed over time.
As we have, I shouldn't say perfected, but as we've refined processes, and I talked about fixed-timed artificial insemination, and I continue to do work in this space, but the improvements are only incremental, right?
And so I've tried to find other ways to enhance reproductive efficiency, right?
And so one of the areas that's important to me is the only way you can generally increase pregnancy or have more cows give birth
is to reduce the number of animals that don't lose a pregnancy, right?
So focusing on trying to understand the fundamental reason around that.
And then I've always had a passion in sort of the...
the genetic side of things.
How can we improve the genetics?
And that's why gene editing and, you know, with the advent and development of CRISPR-Cas9 and the advent of the first clone sheep, Dolly, at the Roslyn Institute in
the UK, that technology has given us a chance to combine those two technologies to generate gene-edited cattle.
And so that's pretty cool.
That's so neat.
It makes me excited to see what kind of technology comes out in the future and how that impacts that.
But as an administrator, I think you go through these phases of where new technologies incrementally change the way you do business.
Right now, we are in a phase of
if we're going to increase our efficiency of food production we're in a phase right now where we need to significantly and significantly advance our work in the use of artificial intelligence machine learning sensor technology and things like that that develop
aids whether they're decision tools or technologies that vastly change the way that we do business and so ai is going to change agriculture for the future
Have you ever seen it?
Oh, yes.
Yeah, I've got several great examples, right?
And so we have our big digital ag group at our Corpus Christi Center has developed a model using drones and satellites.
and big data and taking weather, past and future forecast weather data.
And they predicted, this would have been two years ago, that cotton farmers in the region should harvest their cotton three weeks earlier than they ever have done before.
And those that actually did it got a 10% increase in the total cotton value of their crops than they'd ever got before.
One producer didn't believe it, and he harvested his cotton sometime after July 4th is when they do it down there.
And he told me that he said because he didn't listen, it was about a $375,000 loss by not doing it.
So so there's a tangible example of how artificial intelligence, machine learning and all of the data science can significantly change.
I could make or break somebody.
Absolutely.
On the animal side, you know, we all walk around with phones.
We walk around with watches that keep track of.
Heart rate and all of this stuff, you've seen these aura rings that people wear, right, that are always monitoring something about them, whether it's blood pressure, heart rates, things like that.
um we're starting to use this technology right and it goes back to trying to identify animals that might be sick before they even act sick so traditionally how we would do that is somebody's looking at the animals every day says oh that animal's got droopy ears it looks like it's not healthy we need to go and get its temperature and treat it
well we're using this technology now to try and identify animals that are not doing well before they show clinical signs you can treat them sooner they recover quicker you use less antibiotics you use less treatments and that way you use have less
production losses does that make sense and i know i mean i have a garmin watch and i'm out there all the time and i and i can just tell by how my the app is telling me it's like oh yeah you didn't sleep that great last night and or you may be getting sick because of some some markers right and we're doing that with livestock now
All I can picture is the cows wearing little smart watches.
Yeah, so they wear ankle bracelets, like, or some have collars, some have ear tags.
So there's various wearables, right, that we have now for livestock.
There's even a situation where they were working.
Have you seen these little dog robots?
Mm-hmm.
So one of the big issues in the fed cattle industry right now, so confined animals that are in feedlots just before they go to harvest, they have what are called pen riders.
And these are people that will ride their horses through these pens every day to check the animals to make sure that they're healthy.
Well, there's a company right now that is using a dog as a robot
that is trained to look for animals that might not be well so that it can replace some of the pen writers because there's just not as many of them out there.
Right.
The future is now.
The future is now, exactly.
Is there anything in your work in particular that you're very proud of and that will be your shining work?
You know, I mean, I think that I'm the most proud of is the students that I've trained, right?
I mean, the success that they have, right?
There are some accomplishments that I think will have long-lasting impacts after I'm gone.
But, yeah, so certainly...
I'll say by the students that I've trained, especially the graduate students.
I mean, not that I don't want to minimize the impact on undergraduate students, but I've been very fortunate to have had some phenomenal students that if it wasn't for them, I would not have had the career I had.
They're the ones that probably deserve as much credit.
where they've come up with great ideas and I've just figured out a way to facilitate it.
And so I've got students that are now, I think I have 10 students that are now faculty members and researchers at universities around the world, anywhere from the US down to South America and Brazil.
sorry and Australia and so yeah very proud of what they're doing and how they're training the next generation right and so some of them now already have students that are faculty members and so so to me that's that's the proudest achievement obviously seeing livestock producers around the world
Especially when I travel and they say, you know, we use this system or we use this device that you helped develop.
And it's helped us become more productive.
Those are the things I really get a lot of joy out of.
So in my current role, I think...
the things that are going to be have impact for years to come are some of the infrastructure that I have been able to get built so and I'll give you some examples we just had a ribbon cutting on May 6th of last year
So a year ago to open the new reproduction and biotecnology center out at the Rellis campus.
And so that's, it's the only facility of its kind in the world.
Um, we have just, we had the groundbreaking last week for the new meat science and technology center, right?
So that is something that I've worked on for eight years to get to this point.
Um, yeah.
And so that's a, to be able to figure out how to come up with $130 million and, um,
Put all of that together and spend eight years getting to this point.
Those are things that I think will have impact for the future.
We did a ribbon cutting for a facility up in Canyon in the High Plains.
So there are researchers that are going to help, whether it's cattle producers or wheat producers or whatever it is in the high plains.
My hope is that 30 years from now, as a result of having that facility, they generate results that have impacts for the agricultural folks in that region.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
It's absolutely global.
That's what I'm figuring out from you is that one small little thing here can absolutely change the world.
Yeah, exactly.
So those are the things that I think are...
Specifically when you became the leader here at the department head, what were some of the goals or visions that you really wanted to bring in with you?
yeah so let me talk not so much as department head but as director of agri-life research right I wanted to modernize the agency and modernize internal controls so things that we did internally
um that we are using the latest technology so using electronic things using artificial intelligence to make decisions using data to make decisions and we've we've been able to modernize over time my goal was to increase research expenditures
And that's important, you know, the number itself isn't important, but if we are increasing research expenditures, it means that people who fund the work that we do are seeing the importance of the work so that they fund it.
Does that make sense?
Absolutely.
And so we've been able to increase research expenditures by 53% in four years.
So in 2022, when I started, our research expenditures were 225 million.
This past year, they were 345 million.
And so it's going after bigger, more complex problems.
If you think back 60, 70, 80 years ago, most of the problems that we had to solve could be solved by individual little things, right?
If you wanted to, I don't know, make a cow herd more productive, you could do one or two things that we did research on
and that that would make a significant impact on on a cattle operation well now it's more complex right and so how do we bring disciplines together so if we're trying to solve a cattle problem it's not just a people in the department of animal science right you've got 70 percent of the cost of a cattle operation of feed
feed is going to either be pastures or it's going to be and so the people who grow that feed and how do you get them involved how do you get the health people the veterinarians involved so bringing together trying to solve problems in a more complex way absolutely yeah does does this mean that whatever new innovation that the research side of it comes more nuanced
Yes.
Is there a correlation there?
So you mean the research is more nuanced?
Yes.
It is because some of the changes we make are so incremental, they don't make a big difference.
But if you want to make big changes,
it has to be a multi-disciplinary approach that that has a look at holistically the whole enterprise right and whether it's i mean it could be water quality that has an impact on on ultimate production of chickens right and but if you're a chicken geneticist
the last thing you're thinking about is water, right?
And it doesn't matter how different the genetics are if the water is not good enough quality, right?
And so how do you bring all of those folks together to make big differences, right?
That makes sense.
make people actually interact with each other.
Exactly.
The other thing, though, that I think has been really important for me is to focus on improving infrastructure across the state for research infrastructure.
which allows people to become more productive.
And when you think of all of our research infrastructure and agriculture across the state, most of that infrastructure was built 50 to 90 years ago.
Wow.
Science is very different now.
Technology is very different now.
So how do we get improved infrastructure with improved analytical techniques, right?
You know, it could be lab instrumentation.
Whatever it is, drones, get that in the hands of people that then can go and do good work.
And we think that's paying off.
Absolutely.
It sounds like it.
Thinking back your whole career, what have been some of the biggest challenges that you faced or that your team has faced in our own teams?
Yeah.
Boy, that's...
That's a really good question.
I think
challenges that we have had to overcome are artificial barriers that people put in front of you.
So whether it's a bureaucratic process or a regulatory process or something along those lines, that is a barrier for something good to happen.
And so trying to figure out
creative ways to either get around it or to have conversations with the people that are making those decisions of why their decisions have an impact.
I would say that's been the biggest barrier.
Um,
You know, I think very often too, it's the most researchers rely on funding to do the work.
And I've been very, very fortunate that I've tended to always have a lot of funding, but it's sometimes the best work isn't done
with the funding you get done right and in other words some of my best research are things that we know is going to make a difference but you end up having to focus on something because that's what it's being funded does that make sense yeah exactly and the competitive grant side of things
you spend so much time trying to focus on funding because that's a metric that that you use to run your lab but the impactful work very often isn't the work being funded by so
so funding is probably yeah it is tricky yeah i feel the pain over in the art side of things oh absolutely yes yeah that that's right no it's and and obviously there's a lot more money in the stem fields right you know like like ours yeah yeah um over the course of your career i know we've kind of touched on this but
What has teaching meant to you personally?
Teaching, yeah.
I would, you know, for me, I'd probably lean on this more and say mentoring.
Right.
You know, I think
And I let a lot of my students know all the time that and even my own kids, right, that successful people don't become successful without other people believing in them.
right it doesn't there's not a single person that can say they ended up doing what they were doing without looking back and going boy if this person didn't believe in me i wouldn't have got this job or i wouldn't have got this position okay and it's accepting the fact and being humble enough to accept the fact that um
you are going to have people believe in you or help you along the way and being comfortable with that I've seen so many bright people over the years that I don't know if it's arrogance I don't know if it is a lack of self-confidence whatever it is where they're not accepting help and then 30 years later they look back and go geez
I didn't get done what I could have got done because I didn't listen or I didn't okay I know that is not quite answering the question you asked but I think yeah I think mentoring to me means that you
You try and allow people to build on their strengths and understand what their weaknesses are and give them the opportunity to fly, right?
And so if I focus on graduate students, right?
Every one of my students has a different skillset or has had a different skillset over the 30 years that I've been a faculty member.
None of them are good at everything.
But all of them have some phenomenal strengths.
I can't say I've had a bad graduate student, like a student that I just was like, this is just going to be a disaster.
Right.
But it's so being able to.
As a mentor, being able to understand what their strengths are, help them on their weaknesses and then.
provide some mentoring to let them succeed where I think that their best opportunity is.
Does that make sense?
It honestly sounds like you were built, you were made to be a mentor.
That's the energy I'm giving from you.
yeah and I will admit right I don't personally I don't get a lot of energy or pleasure I enjoy speaking to classes but teaching a class every day
some people are just really really good at that that's not me I love speaking to students anywhere from kindergarten age all the way up but I don't get a lot of energy teaching a class
to be undergraduates or even graduate students where it's a routine every Monday, Wednesday, Friday.
That just, it doesn't excite me.
I just don't get a lot of energy out of it.
I mean, I far prefer to do a lot more one-on-one mentoring or mentoring a group that's sort of working in a mission.
And I really take my hat off to those teachers that do a phenomenal job because they're so good at it.
And that's just not my strength.
That makes sense.
As you said, we all can't be good at everything.
Thinking back to your education, is there any professors or mentors that stick out in your mind as
Yeah, actually, yeah, there is almost every step of the way.
Right.
I can name one or two people that were.
So as an undergraduate student, I have a person who I still remain in touch with today who sort of took me under it.
his wing and really pushed me, right?
I mean, he didn't just, I mean, I was a foreign student, just new to this country, didn't know anybody, but really, really pushed me and was somebody who helped me try and figure out where to go next.
My mentor for my Master and PhD was a phenomenal scientist.
um and him and i still are very good friends today but um you know we were very very different in terms of our personalities and you know i but i really appreciated the fact that he never he he never i mean he yeah he pushed me too but
never did he question the things that I was doing and the life choices I was making and was always very supportive but but he was he was a phenomenal mentor right and probably was the reason I'm still a scientist today yeah it is so
Carrying on about the students and mentors, what kind of skills or values that you hope your students carry with them through their careers?
Yeah.
So there are two things that I think are really important for all students, right?
And I see it more and more now.
One is that
I think that grit probably is more important than almost anything else, right?
It's the have with it-ness to get through something difficult, right?
And really push yourself.
N is far more important than getting an A.
It's far more important than being able to graduate with a 4.0.
It's your ability to grit out during tough times and not let it have a negative impact on you and use it to learn.
I think that that's extremely important.
I tell all of my students all the time and my kids are so tired of hearing it that getting a degree is not a degree in wisdom.
It's a degree in perseverance.
And so you've got to persevere.
There are times that you're going to hate it.
And it's how do you get through that without
hating it, right?
Without hating the process, but knowing there are gonna be difficult times before you get to the end.
So I think, yeah, that's important.
And then having the education is to open a door, but it doesn't keep the door open.
right it's everything else about you once you get a job or once you do what you're doing keep learning keep on making sure that you're becoming a better person than you are the day before right and and so i i tell people that all the time i mean the job isn't going to keep you there at least the degree isn't going to keep you in your job right
It's going to open the door, but it's not going to be the reason you get hired, and it's not going to be the reason you keep your job.
Absolutely.
Fantastic.
I'm going to take that advice.
So what has it meant to you personally or even professionally to be part of Texas A&M?
Yeah, I mean, I'll start off by saying I'm proud to be part of Texas A&M, right?
It's a phenomenal university.
And you'll probably hear a lot of people talk about the core values.
And I think that that's true.
But I think what makes me proud is the type of people
that come here as students and as faculty members and staff for the most part are good people right and so yeah they want the best for themselves for their students and they're just very very good people now beyond that what I'm proud about is that almost any time you say
you're from Texas A&M in some way however that comes into discussion very seldom does it come with a negative connotation so it's what the people have done before we've been here to have built something fairly strong that has given it a reputation to have grown good people that have gone out and made a difference
And so I guess that's what I think about it.
I'm proud.
I tell people all the time how lucky we are to be a part of Texas A&M.
I feel the same.
So switching over topics a little bit.
Sure.
How has the field of animal science and specifically reproduction processes changed since your career?
Yeah.
Um, I think animal science in general has significantly changed.
I mean, in terms of reproduction, um, I think we have so many more tools now than what we did when my career started 30 years ago.
One of the things that I think is quite amazing in all of this
is when you're doing the work when we're doing the research and so on you don't really notice change as much but you know i'm starting to get to a stage in my career now where i'm being asked to talk about progress and change and you know when i give those talks now i'm like
Oh boy, look what has been happening over the last 30 years.
Look at the change.
But yeah, so animal production is very different.
When I started 30 years ago, the average livestock producer could survive by not implementing
technology and implementing genetic selection and implementing things like this the average livestock producer today cannot afford not to do that cannot afford to not implement modern technology okay and so what you're seeing now is the average farmer still or rancher is still in the high 50s or low 60s
But you're seeing a brand new generation of people that are coming in and entering animal science that have this expertise in technology.
They're bringing it into the operations and operations are starting to adopt it at a faster and faster rate.
I don't even know if this has an answer, but from an outsider, I was wondering, is there an ideal cattle industry?
And if there is, what would that look like?
That's a good question.
I don't know if there's an ideal cattle industry.
I think...
I'm just thinking, you know, and the reason is that I think there's no ideal cattle industry is not only, I mean, there might be an ideal way to raise cattle today than meet certain markets that works for you today.
Okay.
but tomorrow the world around that industry is that that operation is different that they have to adapt does that way okay and so i'll explain uh how i mean this take a look at how the consumer has changed in their perception of beef okay in the 80s and 90s people love beef right we ate a lot of beef
and so the cattle industry then was just producing beef and it wasn't necessarily the highest quality beef people just loved it but the eating experience was variable you could go to the store and you could buy a steak and go and cook it and sometimes you'd like it and sometimes you wouldn't right because you might not have prepared it well or the product might not not have been very good
the industry in the US really changed and they started improving the quality, right?
And so producers who might have been able to fit that market and at that time now have to adjust their genetics because the industry demanded it.
But then the consumer
also got into a situation where red meat is bad for you right fat is bad for you so um so the cattle industry is changing and adjusting to that and now we're in a situation where thank goodness
people have started actually seeing the science and it's not necessarily the red meat, it's the carbohydrates, it's bread and sugar and things, right?
Where protein, animal protein actually has a lot of really good benefits, right?
And so now we're in a market where marbling in cattle is extremely important.
Marbling is the intramuscular fat.
that actually helps us have more tender products yep exactly wagyu and then most angus genetics products um and so when people cook that meat it's more difficult to screw it up and so they have a better eating experience right and and now we also have
people that make more money and willing to pay more for their for better quality beef right so the producers that are not have not started producing animals that have better genetics the cattle markets have now shifted that were in the 80s and 90s it didn't matter what size animal went through through the sale barn and to slaughter
everyone every animal is worth the same price based on weight that's not the case anymore an animal that was really good marbling genetics is worth about a thousand dollars more than an animal that isn't right yeah so can you imagine being a producer that was producing poor quality beef right that in the 80s and 90s might have been doing a good job and so they didn't adjust so so it's really difficult to pinpoint what the ideal operation is
and every country has a different system but at the same time I think the ideal operation is the operation that is willing to adjust to what the consumer wants and the market signals quicker I didn't think that was ever going to have an answer because it's too complicated it is
Are there any...
I know we talked about technology and changes in the way we approach things, but is there something that really excites you now that you see coming into the future in new technologies or process?
Yeah, I think we touched on this a little bit, but I do think what really excites me right now is...
I think we're starting to see that people value where their food comes from.
And then coupled with that is the exponential increase in our ability to use data to make decisions and decision aid tools and tools, right?
So AI, machine learning, sensor technology, and then a consumer starting to value where their food comes from.
Yeah, I think those two.
And these last couple questions are like personal reflection kind of questions.
Has there been any turning points in your career, whether it's good or bad, that significantly changed the trajectory of your life or career in general?
Yeah, so, yeah, multiple, right?
I think, and this might be something, you know, back to the mentoring, right?
One of the things I tell my...
students all the time when they're trying to make decisions is is it the right decision it's not really the right decision I mean when you think it's Yogi Berra said when you come to a fork in the road take it right so you're going to come to multiple times in your life where you have decisions to make
Don't sit there and pine over the decision.
Make the decision and don't look back, right?
So in my life, I mean, I think a decision at a very young age, not knowing anybody in the U.S. and coming to study as a teenager to leave a family in Africa, right?
Right.
And not knowing what the future held, but that my plan was always to go back.
So that was one, I think, not necessarily having...
The opportunity to go back to Africa was a big turning point in my career.
And don't regret it at all.
It was sad when it happened.
But I think I've been able to have a larger impact, even on my home country, doing what I'm doing than had I gone back.
That's going to feel good.
yeah yeah that does um and then probably the the last really big decision was i never really thought of being a university administrator right um never crossed my mind it was never something that i aspired to do
but taking the leap when somebody asked me if I would consider it I think has been has been life-changing and you know I look at I look back at it now and every administrative position I've had I've been able to have a positive impact on more and more people and so so those are the probably the big big ones
You've already given some advice, but is there any other kind of advice that you would like to give to people who maybe are interested in this field or just interested in this field?
Yeah, I think there is some advice, right?
I think the folks that will make the biggest impact in the future
in in my my field and i'll just talk about animal science in general um and and maybe even over the entire agri-life research right the thing that i would say are those that are going to be the most successful are going to be the people who are willing to adapt faster um and i'll give you an example
in the past if we were going to look for a faculty member or look for somebody to lead a certain area we would look we would say well we need somebody who's a geneticist right and then we go out and look for somebody who fits a position description
but now when we do that yeah we may broadly want a geneticist but really what we want is we want somebody who over the next 30 to 40 years is going to be able to adapt to needs over that period of time because if we hire if we hire a geneticist today 30 years from now genetics may not be the focus that we need right we need somebody who's willing to adapt as time changes
So I think adaptability is extremely important for anybody.
For young people, I would say most of them want to come out and make a lot of money right off the bat.
Almost everybody wants to do that.
And I would let everybody know to be patient, right?
um make sure that you spend your first five or ten years out of school honing your skills you may not it may not be the most the greatest income generator you may not become a millionaire in your first five or ten years but build on that and then gradually grow through the system and and and take on opportunities yeah don't rush it yeah
I think we have too many people that want to leave and go and start a job right away because they see the dollar signs, but they don't see the investments in themselves.
That's fantastic.
I have two legacy questions.
They've been asked for the last 50 years in these oral histories.
The first is, if you were given a million dollars and you had to use it somehow on this university, does it matter where it went?
Just your pick.
What would you put that to you?
If I had a million dollars, I would probably put it into an endowment so that it would live forever and use the interest from that to focus on graduate education.
First person who says that to me, by the way.
What's that?
You're the first person who's told me that.
Oh, really?
Yeah, that's.
Yes.
So you need cancer.
Yeah.
And my very last question is, how do you want to be remembered?
Mm-hmm.
in your career or personal life that's a good question um i don't know i mean i haven't really thought about how do i want to be remembered i mean my hope is that when i'm when i hang up my shoes and i'm six feet under that people will remember me for having an impact on other people's lives
yeah so yeah i mean i think the accolades in terms of science and things like that i think those are great but i think that's not really what drives me it's it's how do we impact other people's lives you know and and i really want them to
remember that I was hugely passionate about agriculture.
This is the first time I've physically met you in the flesh, and I can even feel that, so I'm sure that's going to be it.
It's going to be your legacy.
Is there any questions or comments that you wanted to...
No, I think we covered a ton, didn't we?
Yeah, I think so.
Yes.
Thank you so much for doing this that way.
Oh, any time.
Yeah.
And if you need more, let me know.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
I'm going to stop talking.